<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "http://apache.org/forrest/dtd/document-v12.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>Welcome to Sandesha</title> 
  </header> 
  <body> 
    <section>
      <title>Overview</title>
      <p>Sandesha is an open source java implementation of WS-ReliableMessaging Protocol on top of Apache Axis.
	</p>
	</section>
 <section>
	<title>Abstract</title>
	<p>The software industry is moving more towards service oriented implementations. Web services play a major role in the above movement and there are several new concerns have been identified as crucial when integrating this model in to the business applications. As with most client server applications reliable way of message transfer is a must for business applications that are implemented using web services.
	</p>
	<p>One such concern is the reliability of the message flow between the client and the service. IBM, Microsoft, BEA and Tibco came up with a specification named WS-RelibaleMessaging Protocol providing a model of message for a reliable message delivery system.
	</p>

	<p>Sandesha is an open source project that provides an implementation for the above specification. Sandesha is implemented on top of 
	<link href="http://ws.apache.org/axis/">Apache Axis</link>(Apache eXtensible Interaction System) that provides an extensive support for web services. The set of features provided by Sandesha can be described as follows.
	</p>

<ul>
<li>

  An implementation for WS-ReliableMessaging with the support to WS-Policy and WS- Addressing. 

</li>

<li>Interoperability with other WS-ReliableMessaging implementations. 
</li>

<li>
A monitor component that can be used to create artificial message delivery failure and out of order delivery scenarios that can be used to test the Endpoint Mangers. 
</li>
</ul>

<p>
Sandesha provides a complete support for WS-ReliableMessaging specification allowing a reliable communication between web services as well as web service and clients. It also provides the INORDER message delivery assurance for the users. 

</p>

</section>

<section>
<title>Commiters</title>
<p>Committer list for Sandesha is as follows.</p>
<ul>
<li><link href="mailto:sanjiva@watson.ibm.com">Sanjiva Weerawarana</link></li>
<li><link href="mailto:dims@apache.org"> Davanum Srinivas </link></li>
<li><link href="mailto:glen+dated+1069472355.725612@thoughtcraft.com">Glen Daniels </link></li>
<li><link href="mailto:nava@opensource.lk">  Amila Navarathna</link></li>
<li><link href="mailto:amila@opensource.lk"> Amila Nilantha </link></li>
<li><link href="mailto:jaliya@opensource.lk"> Jaliya Ekanayake </link></li>
<li><link href="mailto:snimalan@opensource.lk"> Sudar Nimalan </link></li>
</ul>


</section>

<section>
<title>Access the Source Tree</title>
<p>
Anyone can checkout source code from our anonymous CVS server. To do so, simply use the following commands (if you are using a GUI CVS client, configure it appropriately): 
</p>
<ul>
<li> <code>cvs -d :pserver:anoncvs@cvs.apache.org:/home/cvspublic login
password: anoncvs </code>
</li>
<li><code>cvs -d :pserver:anoncvs@cvs.apache.org:/home/cvspublic checkout ws-fx/sandesha</code>
</li>

</ul>


</section>

<section>
<title>Disclaimer</title>
<p>
Sandehsa is an incubated subproject under the sponsorship of the Apache Software Foundation's (ASF) Web Services project. Incubation is required of all newly accepted projects until a further review indicates that the infrastructure, communications, and decision making process have stabilized in a manner consistent with other successful ASF projects. While incubation status is not necessarily a reflection of the completeness or stability of the code, it does indicate that the project has yet to be fully endorsed by the ASF. 

</p>

</section>
  </body>
</document>
